He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
in our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to
know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we
engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation. The union of the
seen and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening. All of those of you engaged in Gigantomaki and also Draco Maki.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast. My co-host Father Stephen D. Young is with us
from Lafayette Louisiana. And I'm Father Andrew Stephen D. Mick where we have winter
in Emmaus, Pennsylvania. And we are live. And if you are listening to us live and not via Memorex,
You can call us on 855-237-2346.
You can talk to us live.
We're going to get to your calls in the second half of the show.
And our dear Matyska Trudy will be taking your calls.
So sometimes people use their sense of right and wrong
to judge God himself.
Is everything that God does good?
If something isn't okay for humans, why is it okay for God?
I'm sorry.
So it's not we're going to be talking about ethics.
It might seem like a dry topic and probably pretty straightforward, just do what's right,
right?
Don't do the wrong.
But it turns out that how you understand what right and wrong actually are, the truth
of what good and evil are and where these concepts come from.
This all makes a big difference in how you understand not only what you ought to do, but
also who God is.
and how you read the scriptures.
So father, are we gonna start with Genesis this time?
Adam and Eve.
Kind of yeah.
But.
Oh, that's a word of that.
It's a word of that.
Before that.
Yeah.
I have to say, so like, you know,
while the intro plays in everything,
I am alone with my thoughts.
You have time to think over there?
And right before we came on live,
So people hearing this recorded won't know.
They won't know I heard someone use the word gumption. Oh
Yeah, you don't hear that too often up here. Yeah, Lee Yankee land and this may be think right
Like if there's a functional difference between gumption and moxie
Here's going to be my functional difference because there's a different energy, right?
Yeah, absolutely gumption gumption has like an old prospector energy. Yeah, and and like he is like
like, not right, I'd be 40s dancing.
Yeah, or 1940s girl reporter, right?
Yes, right.
Right.
Lewis Lane.
But I don't functionally know if there's a difference.
Call in.
So even though it's not related to our topic at all tonight, if you want to call in about
gumption and moxie, go ahead and do it.
We'll host that as a side conversation.
Absolutely.
But in terms of our topic at hand, yeah, why not start in Genesis just, you know, for
tradition's sake.
Alright.
Pretty early on we get the tree of the knowledge of good and evil.
Yeah.
Where these terms are just kind of used.
And not defined.
Good appeared even before that, right?
Yeah.
And that's all there is one.
That's all there was good, tove and Hebrew.
And then evil shows up in the, with the tree.
But they're not sort of defined there.
either one of them.
And the word, Tove, can mean just good.
It can also mean beautiful.
It can mean whole intact.
Yeah.
I mean, the Greek translation, Kalos, which is in the Septuagint, the actual Septuagint.
It means good and beautiful.
And I don't know that it means whole.
Does Kalos mean whole?
Well, if it's used to, so for example, in Exodus.
Chapter two in Moses is born. His mom looks at him and sees that he's. Sometimes it's translated
as beautiful. Seize that he's beautiful and so decides not to kill him. That's wow. But
whoo. But the idea is actually they're more whole or healthy or right like yeah yeah like he's thriving
Yes, fully formed it so yeah
Yeah, but so obviously
And very clearly with once we get to the tree, these terms are being used as an ethical
sense, right?
Or a moral sense might be better.
But even then, you know, it's hard to extricate and maybe we shouldn't extricate good from,
say, beauty or truth, right?
as if they're.
completely separate things. I mean is there in truth no beauty? So yeah so we're
gonna tonight we're gonna be working on understanding these terms and we are
coming at it. This is why Father Andrew is slightly surprised that I mentioned
Genesis. How dare you go off script? That's what have I ever been on script? I
I
know. Well, okay, I was talking about gum shit and moxie a minute ago, man. Anyway, but
part of how we have to come at this particular topic is a little different because almost
all of us who are going to be listening to this and we who are producing it, right, have
been deeply shaped in our concepts of morality and ethics and the terms we use to describe
those things.
by a lot of cultural forces and cultural developments and cultural shifts. And so we kind of have to to get back to what's going on in scripture and what's going on in Christian theology.
We have to first kind of deconstruct some of that cultural stuff.
Yeah, I mean, what is it that makes a person get to a point where they say without batting
an eyelash?
that pineapple on pizza quote is just wrong, right?
Yeah, it clearly isn't on barbecue pizza.
Spicy take.
Did you know that Hawaiian pizza was invented by a Greek in Canada?
I didn't know about Canada, I believe the Greek part.
Yeah, no, it's a Greek in Canada. It's amazing.
Is that what started the anti-Greek riots in Toronto?
But anyway.
I'm making jokes about dark chapters of the racial history of Canada.
Anyway, said your hate mail to...
We're only eight minutes in.
You should pay.com.
Affinity Canadians.
Usually you wait until after 9.30 pm to throw out these hot takes.
So that...
No, all the nice people are in bed.
Right from the jump.
My wife asked me, are you gonna say anything controversial?
And I said, yeah.
And she said, what are you gonna say?
And I said, I don't know yet, but I'm sure something.
right? Well, I'll come up with something. It'll be good. I won't even have to try. Trust me.
Yeah. But so yeah. So, but, but I mean, out of more serious note that the, the dubious nature of
putting pineapple and pizza, right? We to this day, there are humans who throw their support behind
and who justify all kinds of horrible things in certain situations.
that they wouldn't in others.
Right. Or who, I think all of us at times act in ways that in our better moments we know are not correct.
Right. And so that's a lot of shaping that's gone on in our life to cause us to think that,
that
Black is white and white is black, right?
That to confuse what good and evil actually are.
And this is especially true, as you mentioned,
because we're particularly coming at this tonight.
I mean, ultimately this is going to be about what we do,
but we have to really start with God.
We have to start with God.
because if we have a definition of good that doesn't work with God, that's probably not
going to work real well.
Yeah.
And also, as I think we said in one of our really early episodes, humans are theomorphic.
So if we're made to be the images of God, then what does it mean that God is good is a
super important moral question.
Thank you for watching.
Right. And this is something about which there has been a lot of debate over the years.
And the answers to just that question, what does it mean that God is good?
Are at the root of all kinds of theological systems?
Right. Arguably it's at the root of Protestantism, if we're talking about the Protestant Reformers, for example.
Yeah
But so when this topic is addressed out there in the world, if you go and take a
class about this, invariably they will start by assigning because it's short and
talking about Plato's youth of row.
Plato, his dialogues for the most part are named after the person's
Socrates is talking.
to in the dialogue.
Yeah.
So, youth of row is the dude who,
Socrates is talking to,
as usual, he's kind of a foil, right?
Socrates interlocutors do not really come off
as the smartest and sharpest people in the world, usually.
And sort of what occasions,
this particular discussion that's recorded
in the youth of row is that this youth of row guy
is pressing a lawsuit against his own father.
And this in Athenian culture in the four century BC
was seen as this hideously wicked thing to do
to sue your own father.
It was sort of an attack upon your own father,
disrespect.
Who does that?
For your father, right, yeah.
So this was at a public shame, right?
This would bring shame on his whole family, right?
So the Socrates is sort of, well, man, what's up with that?
And Yuthufero defends himself.
His primary defense is that Kronos castrated Uranus.
He refers to the story in Hesiod, where Kronos, Zeus' father,
castrates his own father.
Yeah, and so-
So we're a no sir Uranus if he can do that, you know
I mean, that's suing your dad as much, much less.
You know, you're aware of that, yeah.
Right? And so he says, I'm, you know,
if anything, I'm imitating the behavior of the gods.
And so the way this gets discussed,
and we're gonna deal with the way it gets discussed
in a minute, but I do wanna point out, right?
The way it gets discussed is not at all
What this
dialogue is about in its historical context.
In the historical context, Socrates' counter-argument is, basically, when you hear stories like
that about the gods, you need to just disregard them.
Yeah.
Right.
When you hear stories that are unworthy of the gods because clearly divinity would not work
like that.
And this is part of, as we've mentioned before, the show Plato's overall program of taking
Greek deities and sort of divesting them of their human qualities.
Yeah, he started to turn, yeah, purify the whole thing so that it's acceptable.
Right, to turn them into the forms.
Right, so you take Aphrodite, you bleach out all of her vanity and
petulence and bed hopping and you get love.
Right.
and your beauty, right, those kind of things, right, so you take the
things, you strip away all that human stuff, and you end up with Plano's forms. So that's
what he's actually doing. That's what's actually going on in the dialogue in terms of
four-century BC Greece. But that's not how the youth of roe gets used in terms of today,
right? Your atheist philosophy professor is not going to treat it in its societal context, right?
Yeah.
he's going to, excuse me, pose it as, oh well, Plato is posing this dilemma, right? And you should
, here's one of the tip-offs that this isn't actually what Plato was doing is that the dilemma they
propose assumes monotheism. And Plato was actually a monotheist. Yeah. But like you can read the youth
the Pro and therefore disprove monotheism.
A dialogue written by pagan polytheists has no concept of monotheism that anybody is
really aware of.
Yeah.
And nowhere there does anyone say that Krodus and Urinos don't exist.
Right.
So, but they will say, here's the dilemma.
This is the important thought that they want to press, that they are attributing to the
youth of row.
Does God command things, like when God gives commandments?
Does He command you to do something because it's right and not to do something because it's evil?
Or is something good because God tells you to do it and something evil because God tells you not to do it?
So which way does the cause and effect run?
Yeah.
Is there some kind of absolute morality that God is in conformity with or is morality
just whatever God says?
Right.
Yeah.
And this takes a whole bunch of forms through history, right?
The nominalist realist debates in the Middle Ages, right?
This takes all kinds of forms, as I mentioned, right?
So this gives.
two possible answers. I'm going to say neither of them are good ones, but anyway,
two possible answers to what it means for God to be good. One of those is good
and evil are these objective categories and God is in the good category.
Yeah. Right. He fits in the good box. The other one would be God is good because God
I'm sorry.
He guides what is good.
Right.
And he has called himself good.
Yes, I am the law.
Yeah.
So I can't do my full stalone tonight.
Yes.
Gaze into the fist of dread.
So, right, and then this is posed as a stolema.
And sometimes your atheist philosophy professor
will even try to use this to prove there is no God.
because he's gonna try
I'd say these are the only two answers so that he's going to say they're both bad answers.
Therefore there's no God.
Yeah, setting aside the fact that you might find one of the answers important, but it could
be the truth.
Yes, one of them could be true, even though you don't like it.
Or there could be more possible answers.
Right.
Yeah.
which is why this episode's not gonna be only 20-
minutes long. Yes, exactly. So, but you know, the problems with these two answers start
becoming pretty obvious. So if we say, okay, good and evil are these objective categories,
and God is in the good category. Right? Then right off the bat, we have this standard
that's over and above God.
Right?
It already exists at this higher level than God such that God has to submit to it.
God has to do the things that are objectively good, and he can't do the things that are
objectively bad or evil.
Right?
Well, so this is a problem because where did that come from then?
Who were what created that?
And who or what then would judge God?
to just buy that standard.
And if there is some being that does that,
isn't that actually God?
Yeah, and I mean, this is super common.
This is one of the things that happens a lot
when people look at the Bible
and they see God doing something that they don't like,
they'll say, well, you know, if that is who God is,
then I'm not gonna worship him because he's horrible.
Meaning I have this other moral standard,
which is the moral standard that everyone should be
subject to and God does not live up to it. Right. Right. Yeah. But so I mean, in a cosmic
level, you get this eternal regress of like, well, okay, well, then there must be some actual
God back there further. We talked about this, what we talked about justice, which is a
real problem in certain threads of reformed theology where justice is somehow over and above
God and God has to submit to justice. Right. Yeah. Like, wait, what? Well, then is it justice
really God. So they think they're and yes we
have people who then assume this, right, that there is some access to that standard, which
stands above God, that I can have, and then by which I can judge God.
Right, so this creates an obvious problem.
Now there is a very common way to try to get around this problem.
Some of you may be typing it already.
Go ahead and send the email to Father Andrew.
He never gets enough emails.
We're going to respond to it right here before hand.
And that is, they will say something like, well, God is bound by his nature.
Yeah, he can't violate who he is.
He can't violate his nature.
Yeah.
And his nature is good.
Right.
And then you say, you can say, well, that's just moving the question back because by what standard is his nature judge to be good.
And they'll say something like, that starts to push toward the other answer of, well, no, just his nature is what good is.
it is.
or something similar. Yeah, which is again this idea that there's something exterior to God,
you know, and some of them he has to be obedient to. Yes. The other big problem with this,
this idea that God has this set nature and that restricts what He can and can't do,
is that is not God's nature infinite?
Right.
How can you be bound by something infinite?
How can something that is infinite restrict you?
Yeah.
Right.
Or flipping it around to say that, don't you have to say that God's nature is finite?
The God's nature has boundaries that he can't cross.
Right?
This is a big problem.
for the Christian God, right? So the dodge of, well,
gods are restricted by his nature, that dog don't hunt.
Yeah, and it's really just kind of using other terms to present
the same, right, the same idea, right, right, sort of around
about, right?
on the other hand, right, on the other hand, there's the
other answer. On the other hand, there are also five more fingers. But the other answer
where just whatever God does is good, and wherever He commands us to do is good, and whatever
He tells us not to do is evil. And we just have to go with that, right, that his command
is the cause, that's what makes...
something good or evil.
Yeah, sort of the ultimate arbitrary morality, which sounds bad, right?
But if you decide, well, if you say, well, God is the arbiter, then that sounds good.
Arbitriot means the will, right?
So it's God's will.
It's what he decides.
Yeah.
It's literally arbitrary.
It always cracks me up with my Calvinist friends.
I say that I referred to predestination as arbitrary.
They're like, no, it's according to God's will.
And I'm like, do you know Latin?
But anyway.
So they weren't meant to know that.
But so
One of the problems with this answer is that in a way it doesn't actually tell us what it means to say that God is good
Because in this instance if what makes something good or evil is God's command and
His will then he's not bound by his own command
So he could tell you not to do something, and that makes it evil, but then he can do it.
And it's not evil when he does it.
Right?
There is no, it becomes meaningless to say that God is good.
God is good under this answer, just becomes God is God.
Right?
It just becomes, right?
kind of a meaningless statement, right?
But also then what this suggests is that the universe we live in, the universe that God created
is just completely morally neutral. That giving someone hungry food and murdering them,
there is no actual difference between these two acts. Accept that. Right, God has told you to do one
and not to do the other.
Yeah, but but beyond that, there's no difference. And so if God did tell you to go and start killing people,
you should go and start killing people. And now it's good, right?
So that's a problem. And while it may be very clear to us, why that's a problem,
A version of this is at the core of how ethics is seen by...
But almost everyone today, in the late 20th century, at early 21st century, even by the people
who identify as conservatives.
And the way I know this for sure, and I flinch every time someone says it, is that they
keep using the word values.
Hmm, values.
We value this, we value that.
This is this is
all sides of the political spread, like I said. Folks who identify as conservatives will talk all
the time about family values and traditional values and American values and people on the other
side will talk about how they value diversity and value, right? Okay, here's where that comes from,
this whole concept of values comes from a fellow named Schailer, one of our 19th century German friends.
right who argued that the world will
live in is morally neutral. There is nothing that is actually good or evil right or wrong
in itself, but that different cultures value different things. Yeah, it's just conventional.
It's just the, you know, the social contract, right? Yes. Yeah. Like we all got together and
this is what we decided.
In our society, we value hard work, or we value...
whatever, right? We value certain freedoms and liberties. We value whatever, right? But that can
just easily be, we value genetic purity. We value, right? Dominance, victory, and war. We value,
right? It's this arbitrary thing. And so if you, let me just say, if you don't believe that's actually
true.
don't talk that way. Stop talking that way.
I think for a lot of values. Yeah, I think for a lot of people,
value has just come to be a stand in for, you know, standards or
beliefs or teachings or whatever. But yeah, it's true. When you
say it that way, then it's just sort of a war of who values this
more or how many more people value this. Yeah, I value this, you
value that. Okay, the only place.
allowed to talk about values is sales at the supermarket.
A circus of value.
It's the better value.
Yes. But don't use that term ethically. Honestly, because this is what it entails.
And you may say, well, that's not how I mean it, right?
But the way we talk about things shapes the way we think about things.
Right, it really does.
and the term value values relativizes whatever you're talking about.
It revises whatever you're talking about. If what you're really talking about is the command
of God, talk about the command of God. If you're talking about the commandments of the Torah,
talk about the commandments of the Torah. If you're talking about the commandments of the New Testament,
talk about the commandments of the New Testament. If you're talking about an ethical principle,
if you're talking about a political principle, call it that.
Yeah.
Right?
Don't don't refer to things as things.
you value. Right. Um, as we'll just say, this is what I like. Yeah. I mean, yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. In this society, we like it when you don't murder people. Oh, okay. Well, I'm on to that,
then. Yeah. Yeah. And we also prefer you don't litter and clean up after your dog. Right. Um,
even their heathens play, it planes things out. Right. That should not be planned out. Um,
Um, big...
rewind. Yeah so obviously from it say that's only for us Gen X or as an older. Yeah.
Any kind of you know I imagine there there there was some like elderly person at some point
desperately trying to figure out how to rewind a DVD. Back in the late 90s but remember laser
discs you had to flip them. Oh yeah. Oh yeah. Yeah. There's a forget which movie it was but there's a
movie where the director
just commentary Kevin Smith yelled forget about DVDs laser disk forever. I think it's haunted
him for a long time. But anyway, it was the wave of the future man. Not that far into the future.
Yeah, not not not exactly. Just like a couple of years, but still the future at the time.
Oh, the 90s.
So yeah, so...
Obviously from any kind of Christian perspective,
this idea that the world is totally morally neutral.
Even if we're talking about its morally neutral
until God starts commanding things, it doesn't work.
Right? It doesn't work.
So a way to kind of work with this,
we talked about the God being bound by his nature.
So a way to try to work with this kind of idea
and make
it work in a Christian context to say, well, you know, things are this way because God
commanded them. Is really a way to make this work for Christianity is really found in the
natural law tradition.
Yeah, this idea that God creates the world and puts a certain order into it. And what is
good and evil is written into the order. Right. Right.
So it's not that it's, this moves the action of God that makes things good and evil.
It moves it from some later point, like when he gives the Torah or when he starts issuing
commandments, right?
It moves it back to when he created everything.
That's when he sort of made the decisions about what would be good and what would be evil.
When he created everything accordingly, he created the order of nature in the universe.
accordingly. And now this, this, you know, there are passages in Scripture, passages in the
fathers that we'll talk about, we've talked about some on this show, like of the episode
we did about Jewish astrology, that talk about God revealing Himself or revealing things
about himself or even rev..
feeling the knowledge of how humans ought to live, at least to some extent, through nature
and through the natural order.
So the natural law traditions don't come out of nowhere, right?
They're not just random dodge, like God is bound by His nature.
These have a basis, right?
is a taking off point, right, at least that is valid.
that this is sort of encoded in nature, that it's encoded in us. That's why people tend to have an innate moral sense about what is good.
Even in this case, even with this kind of explanation, we still have the problem of the statement, God is good, becoming basically God is God.
Yeah, um, and not being god up.
being good per se. But then there's also a couple of deeper issues with this, with natural
law and the idea of natural theology, as it developed in the West past a certain point.
Right. And I'm not going to say what point, because then we'd, Father Andrew would just
get 100 emails arguing about, no, it was 200 years later than that, or 200 years earlier.
But past a certain point.
Yes.
That's some.
The first one is then, first problem is, right, Christ comes and reveals God, right,
in a way that is substantively different than the revelation of God that is generally
found in nature.
Right.
So the way we've gone through this on the
show a few episodes ago, we talked about, right? Christ is the logos, right? Incarnate
the logos is the pattern, the order through which all of creation was created. Everything
is created through Christ. There's this connection, right? But still, the incarnation is this
more full revelation of it. Do we want to say that the incarnation of Christ sort of then
has nothing to do with ethics?
Yeah, I mean, if you're gonna say that all ethics, all morality is written into the creation,
you know, from the moment of let there be light or whenever, you know, whatever point you want to say,
then that suggests that
Jesus is kind of in some sense an object.
These would be like other things, maybe.
Yeah, other things, yeah, right.
But morality was already squared away, right through that rule.
Yeah, which, which makes you wonder, you know, why there's so much of this,
if you look.
love me, keep my commandments going on.
Right.
And we also importantly, we don't see, we don't see.
Despite how sometimes the gospels are taught, we go so far as to say we never see Christ
giving new moral commandments that weren't already there in the Torah, for example.
Yeah, well, and I mean, this raises the question of why give commandments at all.
Yeah, why even give the Torah?
Yeah, what do you need that for?
In creation.
Right.
So it should be there.
Second big problem and a related one.
If it's all there, why didn't no one find it there?
And I mean this seriously.
Right? I mean this seriously.
We know too much about the ancient world now.
Right?
Right.
I'm trying to be kind to say John Calvin
Right
John Calvin basically argued that all the principles of morality and ethics
He was part of this natural law tradition that it was all found there is all available through nature
Right and you already use his evidence
How just the Roman Empire's laws were wow
That's because he didn't you know I
I don't know, I mean, I don't know what he thought.
what was really like. Apparently he thought it's way better than it told the other.
It was living in the 16th century. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So I mean, I'm sure he's getting Roman law
through handed down through later European developments. Yeah. And this kind of thing.
The way the way people like in modern democratic societies talk about Greek democracy like it was
anything remotely similar. Right. Right. Right. I have to assume it's something like that. Right.
This is what we just have to have...
to give another plug for Tom Holland's Dominion.
If you want to know what the ancient world was really like
and how Christianity changed it.
Like, like, ancient Rome.
Right.
Is not what needs to be held up.
This example, you know,
Caesar killing a million Gauls
and it's slaving a billion more.
Yay, Caesar is the greatest guy ever.
Right.
It's a vicious, vicious,
rampant slavery, gladiatorial amusments.
Yeah, I mean, read the great epics.
These are the greatest pieces of literature of this world and look at what they glorify.
Like they like literally I mean it was interesting you know like you read the the Iliad for instance
I think I've referenced this a couple episodes ago
But I mean there are a lot of descriptions about people putting spears through other guys throats
And how awesome and fantastic and glorious and amazing and manly and powerful and godlike that is
Yeah, the really amazing part is what the guy with the spirit as throat gives a speech as he dies. I love that well
That's a nice question.
I mean, if we didn't have that, that we wouldn't have the whole trope of, I've stabbed the
dragon through the heart and he has to give a big speech before he dies.
So we need that.
I want that.
When I was a kid, I thought, you know, somebody would get shot or something and it would take
them like a good 10 minutes to die.
Oh, totally.
But there was nothing you could do to stop it.
Right.
Just sit there and listen to them give it soliloquy.
Um.
That's it.
So, yeah, so the truth is that the Christian conceptions of good and evil did have to be revealed.
And they were revealed at a certain point in human history to humans.
Uh,
So, because we could kind of see that that had to happen, we could kind of know that they're not.
At least in Toto, beyond broad strokes, and coded in some way that humans could actually make out on their own.
Yeah. Right.
I mean, you could also argue, right?
Like, when God gave commandments, he was just sort of reminding that what was in the natural law.
But doesn't that sort of suggest that maybe he didn't...
set up the natural law so great.
Well, or you're just, you're not familiar with humans.
Right?
Yes, you think that they were actually noble and just.
That will not commit adultery.
Like, and no one's gonna ask,
well, is XYZ technically adultery?
Yeah.
Right?
Because you could point at,
well, humans have always thought murder was wrong.
Yeah, and they've all defined murder in different ways.
Right, right.
So, yeah, the Aztecs thought murder was wrong.
They didn't think sacrificing foreigners to their gods was murder.
Right?
Yeah.
Everybody thinks stealing is wrong, but how do you define stealing?
Right.
So, if you go beyond, if you go into any actual depth, these moral principles are not self-evident
in the world.
They just aren't.
Yeah.
Right.
How many...
How many, I mean, maybe this just seems so ridiculous to me because I hear confessions.
I don't know.
But, like, well, this xyz technically stealing.
Right, like, I mean, this is all humans do this.
Myself included, right?
We all come up with justifications and loopholes and, right?
All I did was steal a loaf of bread, and now the, the jaundarms are following me for the
rest of my life.
According to the Torah that...
fine. That isn't stealing according to the Torah. But see, the details like that have to be revealed.
The Protected Forer's John Velzone.
So then another element that comes into that has come into this in terms of our popular understanding of
of ethics.
So, what do we even judge as being good or evil?
Meaning, the way we've been talking about it so far, tonight, we've been talking about actions.
Right. Right. Even when you're talking about God, we've been talking about God's actions. Right.
But there is a move that happens once we get into the modern period, starting in the 16th century.
where, well, no, maybe we don't judge, right?
What people do, but we judge their motivations.
Right.
What were they thinking?
What was their intent?
Why my kids say things like, I didn't mean to
and feel like that should be the end of the discussion.
Right.
So when you look at, when you look at,
you did pummel your brother.
I don't know what you're doing.
pre-modern stuff. Like when you look at guides to confession of the Orthodox Church for the pre-modern period, for example,
it will talk about voluntary and involuntary sins.
Yeah, right.
And an involuntary sin in this instance is not like something you did involuntarily.
Right. Like it's not, oh, you had a seizure and you hit someone,
and that was evil that you hit someone while having a seizure that you couldn't control. That's not what it's
talking about.
volunteering is talking about I threw a rock in a guy versus I threw a rock over a fence
and hit a guy.
But in the pre-modern sense, those are both treated as you hit a guy with a rock.
Yeah.
He's dead or he's bleeding.
Yes.
You need a repent of both of those.
The same way.
Yeah.
Right?
isnt ok cause you didnt mean to.
or the one isn't, you know, assault or the other one is negligence, right?
They're treated the same way, right?
But this becomes a big thing in, once very early in the modern period, I've chosen a couple
of examples, totally at random, John Calvin and Thomas Hobbs.
I think I have the first person to ever group those two people together.
Um, absolutely.
So let's give me some ideas, you know, for like a comic strip person.
It's just an idea.
Can you even draw?
Um, I can draw conclusions.
Okay.
Well, that's fair.
I can jump to conclusions.
I have this map.
Oh, where are you?
Anyway.
Um, so, uh, for Calvin, right, this becomes very important.
Because
This is what allows Calvin to say,
nothing humans do is ever good.
Yes.
Right?
Because we're judging actions.
It's kind of hard to argue
that humans never do anything good
if we're just looking at actions.
Yeah.
Right?
Because like the Bible says,
hey, if someone is hungry, feed them.
And so if you have someone
who is feeding someone hungry,
they're doing a good thing you would think.
Yeah, although you...
You know, the total depravity people would say,
oh, your righteousness is a filthy rags.
Right, right.
But this whole idea of motivate,
well, why is he doing it?
Exactly.
Is he doing it for a tax write-off?
Is he doing it to impress other people
without good he is?
Is he trying to turn his way to heaven?
He makes him feel good.
With that works righteousness.
Yeah, it makes him feel good to do it.
So it's not good anymore, right?
You can see how this is generated, you know, billions of neurotic people in the world through history,
who are constantly over-analysing and micro-diseciting everything they do, right? Because of this, right?
Instead of just, I don't know, Christ tells you to do something so you do it.
it anyway. And of course when it comes to God.
right when it comes to God if you're John Calvin, then God has this whole plan that is the whole history of the universe and in the end everyone is going to agree that that is good.
And so since none of us know that the whole plan, none of us can judge God.
So we just have to say that he is good because it's gonna turn out that he was good in the end
and just trust him.
Yeah, because he is, right?
And Calvin, as we've said before, and in Calvinism,
you have this idea of justice, this category sort of preexisting
or external to God, shall we say, right?
Which fits with that, too.
So, under Thomas Hobbes, Hobbes, you know, obviously deals
deals with this in a very different way.
The jack.
Calvin, but Hobbes says, well, all human actions have sort of one of two springboards.
Either they're self-centered, right?
Either I'm doing it for my own benefit, or they're other centered.
I'm doing it for the benefit of others.
And if I'm doing it for the benefit of others, then that's good.
Yeah.
If I'm doing it for my own benefit, that's bad because that's selfish.
Okay. Now, this is an improvement on Calvin because at least you can do good things.
Right.
There is a space here for altruism, right?
That isn't just wickedness by another name, right?
And, you know, I don't want to bash on Calvinism too much.
People are laughing somewhere.
but
Does anyone really honestly think?
Does anybody really honestly think
that there's no substantive moral difference
between me buying a meal for a homeless person
and telling my friends I did it
and me murdering someone?
Anyway, so.
Yeah, it doesn't it doesn't fit.
with human experience, right, to say that all good deeds are actually evil. It just, it
doesn't fit with our actual experience. I have to create this virtual reality in which everything
is just always bad all the time. But I was hoping you were going to say, sorry, Hobzians,
because like we, you know, there's sorry Calvinists in your corpus all the time.
But how many Hobzians are there anymore? Sorry, Leviathan fans, that would be a whole other
thing. It's true. But, okay, sorry Hobbsy Insert.
tigers or whatever. But yeah, so the, the, are we really to believe that every action I take that
is for my own benefit, like caring for my health, if that was something I did, or, uh,
brush your teeth. You know, you brush your teeth. That's right. You try and eat healthy. You exercise.
That's bad because you're just doing it for you.
It's selfish.
Although there is.
There is a point at which brushier teeth is altruistic.
Well, yeah, yeah, you have to brush your teeth purely for the benefit of
those who are going to see you the next day and smell your breath.
That's right for no other reason.
Just put that out there.
Right. And so and and this way of thinking that you find in Hobbes and lots of
other places in modern thinking.
This is what produces the kind of nut bar reaction you get from like
I know.
brand. Right? Who just says that's ridiculous. And so she decides, no, no, selfishness is
good and doing things for other people is bad. Right?
Right.
National rational selfishness. That's yeah, just just like wraps it around. Right? You go get
yours. Don't worry about everybody else. Right? And then goes lives on the government
dull for most of her life. But anyway, yeah, like, like...
It doesn't ultimately work. Right? It doesn't ultimately work. And remember the parable Christ gave us, right?
There's the two sons, God says to the one son, go work in the vineyard.
Or the father says to the one son, go work in the vineyard. And he says,
uh, not man, not today. I'm playing PlayStation. And I may have altered this a little to modernize it.
Um, it's still better than the message.
Yeah.
And but then later he feels guilty and so he goes out and he gets to work, right?
And then there's the other brother who is like, oh yeah, dad, I'm on top of it.
And then never goes and does it, right?
Like Christ asked which one please just father, right?
So doing the right thing even if it's for the wrong reasons or tainted reasons or stupid reasons, right?
or
guided reasons is still doing the right thing. Right? Yeah and the the neurotic
self-analysis doesn't help anything. Also then, so then with this you know we
can't get into anyone's head, right? We can't really get into someone else's head
that did find out will like.
What were they thinking? Why did they do it? Why did they say that? What did they mean by that?
Were they trying to do that? You know, that kind of becomes a dead end when it comes to other people.
You can ironically overanalyze yourself, but it's hard to do that with other people when you're
trying to assess their behavior. So then another very common modern proposal of how to deal with this
is just well what are the
consequences of what they did. Right? Yeah. This seems to try to get back to some of that
pre-modern sense of the action, right? Like, it doesn't matter whether you threw the
rock at the person or you just threw it over the fence, person still got hit with a rock,
right? That was the consequence of your actions. Right? So we'll just deal with that. Right?
Yeah. I mean, but this is very much a live idea, right? Where particularly, you know,
Thank you.
political correctness, right? Where you could say something that for all of your life has
been a harmless thing to say, you know, and not even like not even a little bit mean
or whatever or you know like closet giggling, you know, but really just something that's
a harmless thing to say. But someone heard you say it and they were offended. And so therefore
you must be held responsible.
because the consequence of you saying that was that another person felt something negative.
Right. Right. It's what were the consequences of your speech in that time and place? What were the
results? Right. Yeah. And that also touches on, which will only touch on briefly because
as striving at, but young people.
By this I mean anyone younger than me.
By this I mean most.
of our audience. Speaking and acting are not the same thing. I know you've been told
all your life that speaking and acting are the same thing. You've been taught this.
That saying something and doing something are the same thing.
Yeah, if you say the wrong thing, you should lose your job. You should be canceled. You
should be whatever. You say the right thing. That means you're standing up for whatever.
It's funny, you see this
on social media all the time.
Like I stand with and then fill in the blank,
whoever, whatever.
And I'm like,
I've done nothing to help those people.
Yeah, and what sense are you standing with them?
Like, what is that?
I changed my profile picture.
I'm standing with.
I've done nothing.
Ukrainian flag.
Is not helping anybody in Ukraine.
The Russian flag.
Is not helping anyone in Russia.
Is someone gonna stand up for the truth here?
Yeah.
But what is talking an act to get on the same thing?
And on the flip side, right?
So what saying something mean to you, right?
They are not hurting you.
Yeah.
They're not hurting you.
If they punch you in the nose, they're hurting you.
Yes.
OK?
Talking and acting are two different things.
Talk is cheap.
So but anyway, old man yells at clouds.
But so yeah, but so there's this.
We go by the consequences.
We go by the results.
I mean, it's like what Hadouh said.
What is
love baby don't hurt me don't hurt me it's not talking right don't hurt me no more no more right
he's she's been writing him for a while so he's been able to overlook the hurts of the past
right but now going forward if you love hadaway you have to stop hurting him
I say this to everyone if you love to pat away you have to stop hurting so you've stood up for
the truth today. I'm standing up for
hat away. We're standing with hat
away.
So someone might try to justify this kind of approach by saying,
well, does the Bible say, you judge a tree by its fruit?
Right?
And say, OK, well, so then see the results.
The results.
Right?
If what you're doing is good, it should bring good results.
And if what you're doing is bad, it should bring bad results.
Right?
That's what that means.
Except that's not what that means.
Yeah, I mean the fruit of the spirit, Galatians 5, right?
Love, joy, peace, long suffering, self-control.
It's not...
You forgot the result.
Kindness to this patient's gentleness.
Yeah, like it's not look at the results, it's look at the character of this person.
Right.
That is not a list of results.
That's the fruit of the spirit.
Is the character.
Yeah.
Um.
And the other problem with this, with trying to go by consequences, is right from Genesis in the Bible,
we see how over and over again, one of the main things God does with reference to the evil in the
world is, he, God brings good out of evil in spite of itself. God takes evil actions and brings good
out of them despite them. We've talked about this in terms of why
He allows demonic activity.
Parentingmatic example, of course, is, is, in Genesis, is Joseph, right?
His brothers want to kill him.
They sell him into slavery.
They had no good intentions toward him.
Yeah.
You have it for evil.
God has turned it to good.
Right.
And, but God uses that to save them all from a famine and all of Egypt.
Yeah.
Holy.
So someone might ask
say in the book of Romans, right?
Well, hey, I mean, if God brings good consequences
even out of the evil we do,
why do we worry about ethics or morality?
Why don't we just do whatever?
And even if we're doing evil,
God will come and bring good out of it.
Yeah, I mean, we could just sin and grace will abound.
Yes, total sense.
Right.
And so that kind of
consequentialism might work at a universe where there's no God, right? But if we
live in a universe where God will bring good even out of the worst of human evil,
and we're still working to define what that means, don't forget, but we'll get there.
Then that means we can't just go by consequences. Because there will be a lot of
things that a lot of examples will find of horrible, horrible, hideous human evil,
Thank you.
But where there are good things that happen in it and during it and relating it through it and sometimes even because of it.
Yeah.
But that doesn't justify the evil. That doesn't make the evil good.
Right.
That doesn't make the evil okay. Right.
This is the problem with going by consequences.
Okay.
So,
there we have good old,
the manual Kant.
I can't even. You gotta do at least one con joke any time you bring them up.
I, you know whenever someone mentions a manual can't all I hear in my head is the
philosopher song by Monty Python. Yeah. I can't. I didn't intend that pun but I can't.
The basic premise of that is true. By the way, all philosophers were just drunks.
Basically drunk. Yeah. But so Kant famously comes up with this categorical
a period of this is how
we figure it out, right? This is how we figure out what's right and wrong, right? In the
world, kind of as a God hanging around, but barely, right, in his universe. So he says,
well, here's, you know, this concept of the categorical imperative. The idea there is that
This is an ethical principle that could be applied to everyone in every situation.
the time. Yeah, if it's right and wrong for me, it has to be right and wrong for everybody else.
Yeah, in order for me to be right and wrong.
A categorical imperative. Yeah. Yeah. So, for example, he would say, well, I might be at a situation
where it seems to me like the right thing for me to do is lie for various reasons.
But I should then think to myself, self I should think.
What if everyone lied all the time?
Well that would be very bad.
Yeah, therefore I should not lie at this time in this circumstance.
Yeah, try to remove all context.
Right.
Yeah.
So no reference to any situation.
Right.
So I mean, there's a basic problem.
Any kind admits this that like you can't use categorical paradigms as the basis for all ethics
because he can only come up with a couple of them that actually worked.
Right.
In all possible
And so, but the overarching structure that comes from that kind of
argumentation in Kant, that's called deontological ethics, is
an ethics that's based primarily in duty.
Hmm.
You have a duty and a responsibility to do certain things regardless
of the consequences.
Yeah, I cannot tell a lie there.
Yeah, I mean, and you know, the classic, you know, one of the
classic foils to this as well.
Let's say you are in Nazi Germany and there are oh godwin law now everyone's tuned out anyway
But you know let's say you're not too Nazi Germany and and can't we be somewhere else can't we be in pullpots Cambodia?
Sir, okay, you know and
There's somebody hiding in the residence
There's somebody that the government wants to kill hiding in your house and they say where are they?
You know should you lie to save their lives or should you say well?
I cannot.
of the lie, they are in the parlor, you know, knowing full well that they're going to walk
in and shoot them or take them on to gas chambers or whatever.
Right. And so this idea that there are just these principles, however you want to attain them,
whether you want to attain them as Kant wants to do through logical reasoning. If you want to claim
they come from nature, if you want to claim, if you want to take the commandments of the Bible
and treat them as absolute in this way.
Right you run into these very very practical problems
right these very very practical problems and
Functionally you look at the history of Christian ethics and before that Jewish ethics
And it's very clear for example that when it comes to saving a human life all the other commandments go away
Yeah, there's a sort of hierarchy
Right, this is this is what Christ was always
arguing with the Pharisees about with the Sabbath. Right? Is they all you're not
gonna do this on the Sabbath? Right? You say, well, if your donkey falls in a
ditch on the Sabbath, you pull the donkey out of the ditch, don't you? Out of
compassion for the donkey. So how much more compassion for a human? Right? These
kind of arguments, right? But the point here is Christ very clearly doesn't treat no
working on the Sabbath as an absolutely sacrosanct rule. And neither did
Pharisees for that matter as you just pointed out of that example they had exceptions. Yeah, yeah, right?
Everyone has exceptions, right? You can argue about what should be the exceptions, but yeah
I mean like you know a Sabbath days walk, but if you take one more step than you're working yeah
It gets you know you're in an arbitrary a certain point in the modern sense of the word arbitrary
And so that's why you can argue about it, but they didn't argue that there are no exceptions
Right?
No one ever argued that.
No one in the Jewish Christian traditions
treated, and early Christian traditions,
at least ever treated the commandments
of the Bible that way, right?
So that's kind of a problem, right?
In terms for that kind of view of how to,
to what it was good to be able to try and reduce it
to rules or principles that are derived in some way.
So then the most...
recent sort of attempted this that I've seen. This is the approach taken by Sam
Harris at his recent book. He did not invent this. There are versions of this
going back into the 19th century and even the late 18th century. But he has sort
the most recent version and by the way.
Eddie won't listen to this, who knows who Sam Harris is.
And doesn't know who his mother Susan Harris is.
Needs to go look up Susan Harris.
Here's this.
You didn't think this was going to happen. Did you find her?
No, this was. I was not prepared for this.
Yes, Susan Harris, his mother, was one of the first female TV writers.
She was incredibly successful. She won an Emmy for writing on Hill Street Blues.
She created the Golden Girls.
Thank you.
Sam Harris is very much the fail son of his mother.
If you're upset about that, Sam, call in.
We'll discuss it.
We'll come on your show.
I don't want to.
No, it's behind a paywall.
I won't come on your show.
Okay.
So, yeah.
And so this idea, what Sam Harris does with his version is, well, okay, look, we can all
All agree.
All of us.
a rational can agree that the worst possible world to live in would be a world
where every sentient being because he wants to include a lot of animals. Every
sentient being was constantly suffering the most horrible possible suffering.
That would be the worst possible world. Yeah, so that's possible world would
be yeah, that's hard to argue with right that that wouldn't be the worst possible
world. That'd be pretty bad. Yeah. So the best would be...
maximum pleasure all the time.
Yeah, for all sentient creatures.
That would be the best possible world.
Yes.
And so we define morality by working toward
the best possible world.
Yeah.
Right.
And so things are bad if they cause
suffering to sentient creatures and things are good if they bring joy and
pleasure and growth to such a great.
Yeah, when I was an undergrad back in the before times, one of my friends and co-workers,
this was his ethical theory, right?
And he kind of gave it a nice little star trek he kind of, Paul to it.
He referred to trying to gather as many heatons.
So heatons, you know, the pleasure particle.
It's like tackyons, but pleasure particles.
And the point was to try to generate as many heat-ons for yourself and others.
there's as possible. That was his ethical theory. He was a
self of out atheist. You know, he's some guy. Good guy. But
yeah, that was his, his, he didn't call it heed anism. Yeah.
Yeah. That's what it was. I mean, it is properly speaking.
It's a form of heedingism, right? That's what we think of
what we think of heedingism. Yeah. I mean, we think of
baccadalía, what do we think? Right, right, right. Right.
But there's a kind of like Epicurean, you know, the high, the
beautiful, you know, the glory is the best possible.
Pleasures kind of things. But so but yeah, so earlier forms of this, they would have literally have things called like a hedonistic calculus where they would have
quasi-bathematical and rational ways to try to, you know, compare
Right the the joy that this brings to this many people versus the joy that that other thing brings to that many people and all this kind of stuff
Right, try to make this objective and sort of mathematic and scientific and all of this stuff, right?
And of course the reason we're trying
to make it mathematical and objective and scientific and all this stuff is because
God's pretty much out of the picture at this point for these folks.
So they're trying to think it's a without reference to God.
And here's the functional problem.
Once you've got God in the afterlife and judgment and all of that kind of stuff gone, why
should I care about the suffering of other people who I don't know and will never meet?
Yeah.
Why be altruistic?
Right.
I can understand why I should care about my family members.
people close to me. I understand why I should care about the other people in my city, even my nation, right?
Because I benefit from, right, from all this, right?
But why should I care about starving kids in Africa?
Yeah, never met one.
It has got a case. Never will. Yeah.
Be both of these people.
Like I can't know if I'm done by life in fact, I mean who's gonna say I'm willing to sacrifice to
serve the algorithm of right.
He didn't.
Well, but it's not even that.
It's not even that because the algorithm doesn't work this way, right?
Right.
In fact, some of those kids who are starving
are basically enslaved by Nestle Corporation.
They get, oh, here we go.
Here's the letters.
Anyway, it's enslaved by Nestle Corporation in Africa, right?
They're why I can get cheap chocolate.
So their enslavement and deprivation
is making my life better.
Everyone's quietly hiding their right,
Nestle chocolate every.
Yeah, exactly.
Right.
What, right?
Why should I care about that from this view?
Why should I make my life worse to benefit these people I don't know and will never meet?
Especially because if there is no hereafter, there's not going to be a reckoning.
Yeah, like why, like why should I sacrifice and suffer in my life?
so that other people's lives can be better.
If there's ultimately no, it's just like,
oh well, I guess I'm the loser,
or like I'm willing to accept little losses,
whatever it might be,
because there's no greater good
that we all get to partake of.
Right, it is model.
And this is something that most of our atheist friends
friends haven't reckoned with.
that once you get rid of there being a reckoning,
once you get rid of there being justice
at the end of the day, right?
There's even a problem for some of the,
some of the universalist folks.
Then why shouldn't I be Henry Kissinger?
Here's some more letters.
Why should be
a person who lives his whole life surrounded by wealthy, powerful people lives
in wealth more than three million people dead at my orders.
Right.
More than three people dead, completely debauched, and sexually immoral man
died at what?
Was he a hundred?
He's close to a hundred.
Isn't he still alive?
I don't know.
No, he's dead.
Oh, is he?
He died on my wife's birthday.
here. There's a great gift from God. Oh wow. So I'm sorry. I know you're supposed to be
Gile of the dead. Ed really? I know what the scripture say. How do I know that God does not delight
the death of a wicked man? I'm not God. I'm a sinner. I'm glad Henry Kissinger is dead. Anyway.
Yeah. Yeah. He was just over a hundred years old. Yes. Oh, just over a hundred years old. Right?
I'm sorry. If you're an atheist, right? How did he not do it right?
If we could summon the ghost of Christopher Hitchens who hated Henry Kissinger, right?
Say, hey Hitch, how did he not do it right?
He was wealthy and powerful, sexually decadent, his entire life lived to be a hundred.
Blood all over his head.
How is he not living his best life, right?
As Christians we know there's a reckoning.
without
Without that, without there being some kind of reckoning, there is no way to construct a reasonable ethical system like this.
Because most of the wicked people in the world get away with it.
Which is, you know, of course, repeated in the Psalms over and over again.
Yeah.
If there's no God, right, then the wicked just all get away with it.
Yep.
Or if you're a universalist.
Well, on that bright and cheery note.
Uh, man, all that.
There's gonna be like Kissinger people emailing you.
There's gonna be like,
I think, okay, Nestle Crunch fans emailing you.
I mean, okay, I will understand the Nestle Crunch offended,
but if I have people like defending Henry Kissinger to me.
Oh, yeah, no.
God bless you.
That'll be next level.
I'm sure they're out there.
All right, well, that said, okay, this is the end of the first half
this episode of the
of spirits we're going to be right back after this break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
What are we to make of the unseen world and spiritual warfare?
I'm sorry.
The Lord of Spirits, book version, is now available at store.ancientfaith.com, written by Father Andrew
Stephen Damick.
To the modern mind, dragons and demons are just the inner demons of psychology.
And angels are often reducible to the better angels of our nature, that is to our better
human impulses and virtues.
of spirits is really about psychology.
But to the ancient mind of...
millennia ago, even up to the pre-modern mind of just centuries ago.
These are real beings with personal presence who inhabit our world and affect us.
Father Andrew provides a distillation and explanation of the material in the popular podcast The
Lord of Spirits, which he co-hosts with Father Stephen D. Young.
Get this brand new book today at store.AncientFaith.com.
store.Ancient Faith.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
I haven't, and during the break I did not get any pro-Kissinger emails, so we might be
in the clear.
I don't know.
A lot of people will be listening to this tomorrow.
So yeah, yeah, I'm pretty sure that was on no one's bingo card for 2024 was father Steven goes off on Henry Kissinger
I mean if someone had said to me
What is the likelihood that that will happen? I'm like oh hundred percent
Yeah, I could see that happening. Yeah, yeah
It does check out
What people thought was at the works here?
y'all thought he was gonna go off on Sam Harris but no
No, no.
Yes, so welcome back.
At least I use someone other than Hitler as an example of the most evil person who's ever lived
I know. I mean Godwin's law doesn't mention Henry Kissinger by name
But
Yeah, yeah
so yeah, we're talking about
goodness and evil
here on
Lord of Spirits Podcasts and we just talked about
a number of attempted models, you know, by which people judge God, by which people judge
right and wrong for humans, and we mentioned some of the difficulties that those models have.
We have not yet put forward any solutions. I think this will be a classic Lord of Spirits episode
in which we would do not get to the answer until the sometime of the third half. And actually,
I think this one is towards the end of the third half. Yes. So, you're not a journey people.
Exactly.
A board dead boat, theses here captain will take you on this trip.
Okay.
Right.
So what exactly is so evil?
So the first half we're mainly talking about what's good.
Right.
Now we're going to kind of talk more about the concept of evil.
Right? And what that means.
And there may be folks thinking to themselves that, well, it's just the opposite of good, right?
So whatever we say good is, he was the opposite of that, right?
Yeah, well, but we do have, by the way, we have a caller from Tennessee, who is calling in,
although his telephone says he's from North Carolina, but that's how it goes, I guess.
That's shady.
I know, I know.
But it's still the south sort of.
Yes.
Is Tennessee the South?
I'm just hearing crackling. Are you there? William? Oh, we're having some trouble getting
hold of the creeper in the Twin Peaks Revival. I know. I know. Well, actually, I never...
You know, Twin Peaks is too creepy for me. I've never watched it. I can't even do Doctor Who,
I think, as we've discussed this before, too creepy for me. Something about we just like
Maybe for 8 year old.
Yeah.
That's like being to date your own.
I'm very tender-hearted, you know.
I guess.
Where's my conscience has been seared as by a hot iron?
That's right.
Well, God willing, we'll be able to get William back here.
Call us back.
And he won't just have that crackly sound.
OK, so William, are you there?
Well, speak to us, William.
Who did this to?
William, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Oh, just got that lovely crackly sound again.
I feel like he's communicating, but it's just, I don't speak that, that my worst code isn't that good.
Batman would be so disappointed.
Blink three times if you're being tortured by Canadians.
Blink five times if you're being tortured by New Zealanders.
Anyway, I hear him blinking, but it's just not coming through.
Alright, well, we'll just have to...
I have to roll on.
But thank you for calling, Liam.
Good try.
I don't know how Canadians would even torture someone.
I don't know.
We give them only small portions of Poutine.
You can have really soggy fries with your Poutine.
That's right.
I'm continuing.
I'm continuing the horrible harmful stereotype of Canadians
that they're very polite.
Deal with it.
So yeah, so we're going to talk about
evil. And as I said, that may, you know, it may seem obvious, right? We may be able to give some obvious examples of things that are evil like Henry Kissinger, but
the way in which evil in particular and its relationship to good have been conceived of
in the history of humanity, the recorded history of humanity at least has changed drastically.
It has changed drastically.
And this is, we kind of alluded to this a little bit when we were talking about the fact
that sort of no one arrived at Christian ethics through natural law before Christianity.
But that is really the pivot point.
That is really the pivot point.
and we, that was just...
We did get a comment from one of our Canadian listeners, and she's actually called in in the past.
This is Catherine of the Great White Zaphone.
She says that Canadians torture people with excessive politeness.
Oh, they just ramp up the politeness.
Yeah, they're really sorry.
like the gameter poutine and they keep asking about your drink like every three seconds.
Right. I mean that would work on me because there's kind of only so much that I can handle. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. So when I say that Christianity is really the pivot point, that's not because we're not talking about the Old Testament or Second Temple Judaism.
It's because, right, ancient Israel, Second Temple Judaism, weren't taking the view of good and evil that was revealed to them
scriptures and sort of proselytizing the world with it the way Christianity did.
Right. And so that's why it's Christianity in particular that marks this pivot point in terms of
how most of us think about it. But so when you read in sources that are talking about this that are
before that are pre-Christian sources.
What you find is that the idea of, say, a good or a bad person.
right? This is a good person. This is a bad person. It's very similar to the idea of like a good or bad chair.
Right. It's good or bad apple. Yeah, it's not good and evil. It's sort of, you know, better and worse. Right. It's a quality. Yeah. Right. This is a good chair. You know, wouldn't say as opposed to an evil chair. No, as opposed to a crappy chair. Yeah. Yeah. As opposed. Yeah. As opposed to a rickety chair. Or an uncomfortably bad apple. Yeah.
or it uncompl-
chair. Right. It's about capability, performance functions. Right. Yeah. Yeah. And yeah,
has certain some of the qualities that make it a chair are very excellent, right? Like comfort or
whatever. Yeah. Or an apple, right. The bad apple might be just like a rotten apple and apple,
it's not ripe yet. An apple that's right. Where's a good apple might be big and ripe and
and...
juicy, etc. Right?
And so this is how humans were looked at.
There wasn't really a concept of good and evil the way we think about it.
Right?
They were like governing particular actions or this or that.
So it was, this is a better person.
This is a better human.
This is a worse person or a worse human.
Right.
If you're strong, if you're good looking, if you're powerful, if you're wealthy, you are
of how it goes.
You are better. You are better.
Right. You are good.
If you're poor, dumb, unattractive according to your
society, physically weak, sick, disabled, right?
Whatever, then you are bad.
Right.
And so ethics at this point, right?
When you look at like Aristotle's ethics, ethics is,
Well, okay, how do you be a good...
person, but it's how to be a good person in that sense. Right? It's how to be a good person
in the sense of, you know, how to be courageous. Yeah. Particularly how to train a child to be
courageous. Yes. Right. Or how to train a child to be sort of a generous benefactor. Right?
of the arts, how to, you know, for Aristotle, humility is a vice.
Right.
Because for Aristotle, all virtues are a mean between two extremes.
So on one extreme, he has people who are sort of arrogant and take more credit for themselves,
think better of themselves than is true.
But then on the other side, you have humble people.
Right.
And he says, no, that's bad, too.
That's just as bad.
Right.
Yeah, because both are lies, effectively.
You want to be a person who has it completely ac-
sense of how great you are. Yeah. Right. Right. Right. But it's all about it's you know it's it's
cultivating virtues but it's not really the way we use virtue. Right. It's cultivating virtue
in the way that like an exercise program for an athlete is cultivating virtue. It's cultivating
excellence at a particular sportive activity.
Yeah, and you know, within this
context, right? Like those famous words from what is it the American Declaration of Independence,
you know, we hold these truths to be self-evident that all men are created equal.
That is actually not self-evident, you know. That only works in Christian ethics.
It wasn't before Christianity. Yeah. That only works in Christian ethics. Everyone's not created
equal. Some people are bigger than others, some people are smarter than others, some people are
we're better looking than others.
Like, stronger than others.
Yeah.
like, uh, we're, you have different talents.
Right.
It's, it's, it's not self-evident.
Yeah.
It's, it's, it's revealed, but it's not self-evident.
Right.
You know.
And this is why, for example, until things become very extreme, until things get to the
point of madness.
Right.
Uh, you see, for example, with Roman emperors and with kings and stuff.
tolerating what we would consider very evil horrible behavior.
like tyrannical behavior and all these kind of things because for them it was like being
a college athlete nobody cares what you do as long as you're good on the field. And it
no. Kind of true. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. But it was sort of that thing. Right. This person
is very good at what they're really doing which is being a general, whatever it is that
they're doing, they're really good at it.
And so their personal
behavior and that kind of things that we would judge in terms of good or evil.
Right? Didn't enter into the picture in the ancient world. Yeah, right? Like the NFL has showed us all that you could be very good in a particular sporting activity
and do impressive feats of human athleticism and be a horrible person from the perspective of good and evil. Right?
categories that are going to come later.
So in the ancient world, though, again, we're going to see categories of good and bad.
So what do you do about bad people?
Right?
Well, they're not evil people.
Remember, they're just bad people.
So there's no concept of like, oh, well, we need to punish them for the evil thing they
did.
Any of that kind of thing, right?
It's the idea that, well, okay, this person isn't very bright, right?
We can extract a certain amount of labor from them.
So they were born to be a slave.
Yeah.
I mean, you know, these ideas come up, right?
They're used, frankly, to justify slavery in the United States.
This was the scientific view.
Was it certain people who look certain ways are made by God to be subservient?
You know, like this is, this is, this is,
of it's a pagan pagan idea that comes back and gets put you know with Christian clothing
on it early early 20th century as Western nations start to secularize eugenics here it comes. Yeah
which is just it's just pagan anthropology coming back. Yeah yeah and this is you know
wedged slavery but hey since we're giving different examples tonight um there's a lot more
Remember this in the US that people really...
This is just something that went out in Europe
and like Germany and stuff.
You know, everyone, you all learn in American history class
about all of our window homes, you know,
the great jurist, the Supreme Court Justice.
Sometimes you should read his majority opinion in the case
where they said it was legal for the government
to sterilize women by force.
In which he says, and I quote,
How many generations of embass-
souls are enough. Wow. And they named it town in North Carolina after
him. Wind, wind, oh, it's just east of
Raleigh. Oh, my soul wind, oh, like, no, yeah. So yeah, and that
is as Father Andrew said, that's a revival of this old pagan
anthropology. Yeah. Right. Where nature, the idea of nature is
that each person.
has a nature. Right? So Aristotle could talk about there are people who are by nature slaves.
That's all they're good for. Right? That's their position. Right? And of course,
Aristotle is going to say women are sort of defective humans as I've put it out before. I do
want to say to be fair to Aristotle even though he does say that and that's obviously horrible.
He is the first person in the Greek world to say that women were at least...
least human. It's a start. If you read the medical texts in the
hemocratic corpus, they're pretty clear that women are in different species.
They're not human. So Aristotle took a half step in sort of the right direction.
Yeah. You thought women were human at least, just defective ones, right?
Right. But so, so that's how nature was seen, right? That each human has a
nature and they need to be pl-
into a place in society based on that nature.
So if they're one of the wise ones,
one of the smart ones,
they need to go to the academy and become a philosopher.
And if you're Plato, who's one of them,
you should really be ruling the city,
but no one will listen to you.
If they're physically, they need to become an athlete
or they need to become a soldier,
they need to become a general
if they have a strategic one.
Everyone gets plugged into society
based on their individual.
nature. And virtue is just being really good at something, being excellent at something.
Right. It's not... I mean, it is a moral category in terms of how they saw morality, but it's not a
moral category in terms of how we see morality. It's just being excellent at something. That's what
RIT that we translate virtue, it actually means, is like excellence. Yeah. You're excellent at
That's something you're really good at it.
And so there is no shared human nature.
Right.
There's not the idea that human nature is a thing
that all humans share, that all humans have the same nature.
At all, remotely.
Right.
People on top are the best people.
People in the middle are people on the bottom are the worst people.
Right.
Yeah, I know.
within paganism in general, there's even a sense of separate creations like different
people in different city, states and tribes were created separately by various gods and
yes.
So like this is built into the whole system.
Yeah.
With different qualities for different purposes, right?
So when Saint Paul goes to these nations and is preaching that there's one human nature,
Let's see Paul's getting that from the Tories, getting that from Genesis.
that male and female humans, all of them are created in the image of God, that there's one human nature. This is
a massive bomb dropped on on the whole way humanity is thought about.
Yeah, the whole notion of human rights is
Christian. Yeah, the idea that the emperor and the lowest slave woman, right, the lowest slave woman have the same human nature.
are human in the same sense and have the same dignity before God is an unbelievably revolutionary
idea.
Yeah, I mean, that would have been a massive joke.
It was absurd.
Yes, it was absurd to the Romans.
Yeah.
Right.
It was absurd to the Romans.
But it's basic to Christianity.
And this is another one of these places.
is crept back into our secular society.
You know, I gave some grotesque example there
with Oliver Wendell Holmes, right?
And eugenics and stuff, that we now see as grotesque, rightly.
But in a more subtle way, right?
There is a certain strand of thought in our society.
And it's frankly a strand of thought
that is politically on the right,
that I think makes it attractive to some people.
who are more traditionally religious, shall we say, even though this is not a religious idea, right?
And that is that this kind of anthropology creeps in in a softer way in the sense that
people will argue that the current structure of our society is natural.
Right?
So the people on the top are
society like Elon Musk and Jeff Bezos. They're the smartest and hardest working people in our whole
society. That's why they're the richest people in the world. You definitely get that.
They're sort of like weird kind of awe for them. And I wonder what kind of sky what color the
sky is in your world. But still. Like have you seen Jeff Bezos laugh? Anyway.
And then anyone who is, you know, poor.
right? The poor they are. Well, that's natural too. They're that way because they're not as smart,
they may be that choice. That's natural. That's right. And the fallout of that idea is we shouldn't do
anything about it, especially at the lower end. We shouldn't do anything to help people who are at
lower end because I mean they're there because that's what
they're going to be. That's just who they are. Right. That's their nature. So we shouldn't
do anything. Right. If you're someone who has fallen into that kind of ideology through
politics or something, I would deeply encourage you to start reading the homilies of St.
John Chrysostom.
Because a lot of the homilies of St. John Chrysostom
are
the original version of this. Yeah. Because he's got a lot of people he's preaching to, especially
Constantinople. Constantinople more than Antioch. Who are barely converted pagans. Right. Yeah.
They've come to the doors and become Christians for a variety of reasons. Some good, some not so good.
But they still have this basic pagan worldview. And so when he wants to talk to them about the poor,
or he has to overcome this.
This idea that there's somehow supposed...
to be poor, or their poor because they're bad, right, or they're disabled because they're
bad, right. And so allow me to suggest that to you. If you've fallen into that way of thinking,
I think Saint John has some things to say to you that might help cure your soul of that
particular delusion. But so this is the ancient world's view. As we just mentioned, with
Paul especially as he's going and bringing the faith and a whole new view of
the world and of God and of everything to these pagans. There's this massive shift
where now a biblical view of this is adopted and the paradigm is no longer good and
bad but becomes good and evil.
Right. Becomes good and evil.
And despite all that stuff we talked about
at the first half, that's influenced us,
that different philosophical stuff
and ethical reasoning stuff.
The scriptures don't primarily talk about good and evil
in terms of ethical decision making
or in terms of abstract principles and arguments.
Right, about what is good and what is evil, right?
There's no calculator.
is hedonistic or otherwise, right? There's none of that. Evil is presented from the start,
meaning from Genesis, right? As evil is the power of sin which brings death in the world.
And I mean, I think it's notable, right? One of the earliest Christian kind of catacisms,
which has a lot of ethical stuff in it, the Dheedaki or Didadak, I don't know, DIDA,
They say D.K. if they're.
D.K.
Yeah.
Excuse my Greek pronunciation of Greek.
You know, that it starts out with, there are two ways, the way of life and the way of
death.
It's notable.
It doesn't say there are two ways.
There's the good way in the bad way.
It's the way of life and the way of death.
Yeah.
It's where they lead.
And so I remember sin, right?
First place, Sin is talked about. First place the word occurs and the whole Bible, Genesis 4, right, with Cain.
When God says, and we've just talked about this other show before, but it bears repeating,
Sin is crouching at your door. It wants to master you. You must master it.
That's not Cain. You know, I gave you these commandments and you're mad at your brother and I think you're about to break one.
That's not the way.
is envisioned. Right? Sin is envisioned is this force, this malignant force that because
of the expulsion for paradise, it's loose out there in the world. And it comes for people.
Right? And it wants to master them. It wants to take control of them. And it ultimately wants
to destroy them, to kill them. That's what sin is. And that's what evil is. Right? That's
evil is. And death, right, is again, death is not just depicted in the scriptures as, uh,
you know, well, this is the point where your soul leaves your body. This is the point where
your heart stops beating. This is the point, right. And that's the way you think about it in
in modern terms, right, in terms of ancient pagan terms.
It's not part of this circle of life, right? This cycle that just repeats and repeats and repeats, right?
But death is this devouring destructive decay.
Then again, is that work in the world?
It is not natural.
It is not good.
It is evil.
And so evil, biblically, evil
in the Scriptures, evil is whatever in slave's humanity.
Zousin has talked about, mastering it, right?
And it enslaves you.
And evil is whatever brings death and destruction
to humanity and to the rest of the creation.
So from that understanding of evil,
that you get right from the beginning of Genesis
and all through the Scriptures,
You can, right, sort of come up with a definition.
of good and contra distinction.
Over against that.
So over against that, you could say, OK, well, if evil is this power of sin that's at work,
then good is justice or righteousness.
It is things being in good order.
And you can say, well, if evil is death,
decay and destruction and death.
death, then good is life, right? Good is life. And these are categories we've talked
about before. Yeah, a lot. But it's important, again, that we double down on the scriptures
understanding of life, right? The word life, the scriptures is not just talking about biological
functioning.
It's about the fullness of what God made something to be.
Right.
Perfection and not perfection is in like,
like what a perfect little child you are,
meaning you know, they don't ever do anything wrong.
But perfection like this has been brought to perfection.
This has been refined.
This has brought to its fullness, its growth.
Right.
So it's flourishing.
So we're talking about human life, real human life
and the scriptures is human flourishing.
Right.
Plant life is plants flourishing.
Animal life is animals flourishing.
This is what life is.
This is why you can get the things that we get in the New Testament where Christ could
say, I've come that you would have life, and that more abundantly.
That doesn't mean you'd live a lot of years.
Yeah, no, it means full living.
Yes.
That is this flourishing, right?
this is life to know you the only true God in Jesus Christ.
to whom that was set, right?
That is what it means to be alive.
That is what it means to flourish as a human,
is to know God, right?
In Jesus Christ.
And we've talked before about how these are not exclusive things
that order and life are interdependent, right?
That it is things being in good order
allow life to flourish, right?
And...
And flourishing life is necessary to have good order and for it not to just be tyranny, right?
Like a parking lot is a certain kind of order, but it's not flourishing with life.
And you know, one of the paradigmatic examples in scripture of this is the beginning of the book of Exodus.
Right, where the Israelites are flourishing.
They're growing a number.
They're flourishing in the living of the Nile Delta.
Everything is good, right? But Pharaoh comes and Pharaoh is the king. He's the figure of order
of justice for the Egyptians. He's the one who sets the order and enforces the order,
but he comes not to use his commands and his ordering capacity in order to help the Israelites
or even the Egyptians flourish, but the exact opposite.
Yeah.
He comes for population control.
He comes to kill, right, and to destroy.
And so, you know, here at this point,
as we're nearing the end of the second half,
we've kind of got a working definition of good
over against evil.
And this is a good starting point, right?
and this is a good, we've arrived somewhere.
But we aren't done yet because that definition of good doesn't necessarily work to describe God.
When we say God is good, we don't mean that He is in good order and His life is flourishing.
Right?
At least not quite.
Right? So there's a little more we have to say.
We have to say about that.
And part of the
Reason why this working definition we're at of good on the one hand and evil on the other
doesn't apply to God is that we're going to say that God is good and not evil. God and
evil are not equally ultimate. Yeah. Evil is not the opposite of God. Right. That is
always existed somehow. Right. Not the case. So we have a little more work to do in terms
of what it means that God is good.
And that's what...
but the third half is for.
All righty, well, we're gonna go ahead
and take our second break and we right back
with the third and final half of this episode
of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Robyn Phillips' book, rediscovering the goodness of creation, offers a manual for recovering
nostics and shows how the church's polemics against this heresy have fresh relevance today.
In his foreword to the book, Father Stephen D. Young writes, with this book, Robyn Phillips
explores the way his own religious experience and way of life was shaped and its intersection
with the gnostic experience of God and the material world.
Stephen continues.
Commending this book for addressing the way cultural factors have shaped modern Christianity
and for showing how each of us can counter these factors and shape a new Christian consciousness
for ourselves, so that the propositional statements of the Christian creed become real lived truth.
Father Stephen concludes by writing,
Phillips has made this beginning himself within his own person. This allows him to describe the
landscape and leg guide posts for those who would follow him.
While each person is shaped by larger cultural and community forces, those forces, those communities,
and the culture cannot be corrected and transformed of themselves.
The change must begin within the minds and hearts of human persons.
The change begins with Phillips and with the reader.
It ends with a cosmos transfigured by the glory of God in the Lord Jesus Christ.
Rediscovering the goodness of creation a manual for Nostics is a
at store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
That is the conversion for Robin Phillips.
was expected, but the power aid commercial that played only in certain markets before
that, that was a little weird, not something I thought I'd hear on it.
Well, yes.
Anyway, I was trying to come up with a good springboard for the joke, but it just wasn't coming
to me.
You can tell it's approaching my bedtime.
Yes.
It is.
I know.
now. I do live in the future as compared to you. So, yes, all the way in the year 2000.
I'm sorry, Dave. I can't do that. Right. So we're talking about goodness and evil and
who is God with relation to all of that and what are we supposed to do? We're taking a bold stand
and that people should do good stuff and not evil stuff.
Yes.
And...
Henry Kissinger has been referenced.
Yes.
Same Harris.
And always take a few pot shots at Calvinists and ancient pagans.
Yes.
Typical episode.
So.
Yeah.
So now, as we mentioned at the end, right before the Powering
Commercial, at the end of the last half, we have a little more work to do in terms of
what it means that God is good.
And what we have to take into account, we in particular, on this show, the Lord of
Spirit's podcast, is what we've said over and over and over again on the show repeatedly,
at infinitum if not ad nauseam, that God always acts with absolute freedom.
That is absolutely free.
And so we're going back to some of the things we talked about the first half.
There are a lot of things that are ruled out by that, right?
Ruled out by that principle.
But what do we mean by it?
Right, when we say that, we've put that in certain terms, like the idea that
God has to obey some kind of justice that stands above him, right?
We said, well, that's out.
We censored the-
are out because of God's freedom. But what do we mean when we say God is absolutely free? So first of all we
mean there is God is affected by no necessity. There's nothing necessary for God to do. There's nothing
he has to do. Right. Like, like he must punish sin. For instance, right. As some theologians have said.
Yes, yes.
There are no
Strictions of any kind on God. There's nothing God can't do
Any argument prefaced with God can't to blank is gonna be problematic right
It's gonna be problematic or it's gonna be the kind of question asked by a simpleton like good god create a rock
So heavy he can't lift it right yeah, that's that's I mean
That's
It's just like, you know, saying this sentence is false.
Yes.
It's just pure contradiction like.
If you're a teenager at an atheist,
and you think that's a good argument, it gets God.
Read a book.
Anyway.
Any book, really?
Yes. Any book.
Like Harry Potter will get you past that point.
Like the monster at the end of this book.
We'll get you past that point.
Exactly.
Good night, Moon, even.
We'll probably take you past that's a good argument.
Um...
So God being absolutely free also means that with God there is not any kind of teleology.
There's a $5 word. What do we mean by that? Well, for me as a human, right, I have a
tell us an end, right? There is something that a mature human person, like Father Edwin was talking about
in this way, right?
Maturity, completeness, right?
I was born...
is a gigantic baby with teeth but that was not my final form. I did like I continued to grow even
more giant and get more teeth and hair and things. Are you reached level 9000 yet? Yes. What 9000?
Anyway, so I continue to develop. An acorn has its end and oak tree that it is growing towards
that is sort of its full form.
Obviously, God is not in some kind of nascent stage of Godhood where he's going to develop
into full Godhood down the road.
Right.
Um, unlike all the pagan gods.
Yes.
And so there's no way to apply that kind of reasoning to God.
Right.
But we also may never be say God is.
absolutely free that there's nothing that can act as a cause on God. There's nothing
anyone or anything can do that will cause, right, God to do something. That's how
side of his own will, right? So he's not the force because as Obi-Wan once said,
the force will obey your commands.
Yes.
although you know, midi-chlorians, whatever.
Um, heresy, heresy.
But, right.
So I believe it was Archimedes who said, you know, give me a place to stand at a log
enough lever and I could move the world.
Well, there is no place to stand.
There is no log enough lever to move God, right?
Yeah.
Which is why, frankly, satisfaction, so, theology implies that God is not free.
Oh, you stepped in it now.
Oh yeah.
Let's have it's after 9 p.m. Eastern so I guess a whole bunch of people on Twitter who are gonna say you're not a Christian now so basically like every other day.
That's right.
So, right there so there's no right he's free.
free. And this is, right, this absolute freedom that God has is one of the ways in
which he is not like any other thing.
He is not like any created thing.
I shouldn't say other thing,
because he's not a created thing.
This is one of the ways in which God is not like any created
thing, right?
Including the other gods who are created things.
He is not like them, because none of them are free
in this way.
No human is free in this way.
No woodjuck is free in this way.
There he is.
nothing else, right, that is free in the way God is radically and absolutely free.
Okay, so within this, we need to talk about here comes the orthodox theology stuff.
We need to talk about the distinction that gets made in orthodox theology between God's essence and his
energies. All those things I just said about how God is absolutely free,
I said about his essence.
I said about who God is.
That's why all of them, you may have noticed,
were negative statements.
Yeah, he's unrestricted.
Yeah.
No, you know, not subject to necessity,
not, you know, heading towards some tealos.
Right.
There's all just ways in which God is not like.
Right?
Any creative thing.
No positive statements about what God in His essence is like
because we can't.
God is essence. We could just know that it's not like any created thing, right?
But what that means is, and why that's important for our conversation tonight is that,
when we say God is good, because again, this is one of the things we want to define tonight,
when we say God is good, we're not saying that about His essence.
Hmm.
Good.
positive statement and we don't know his essence. We're saying that about his energies.
We're saying that about his energies. So good is about what God does. Good is about
what God does. Not some statement about his essence. Now, we need to explain again,
Ah
I'm pretty sure we've done this on the show before what we mean by energies
Every episode is somebody's first right and some people may not have heard this before a lot of people may have heard this explained very badly before
But what do we mean when we talk about God's energies as opposed to his essence is pretty clear right God in his essence
Right, God is He truly is God.
is known to himself as God.
Yeah, in himself as it were.
But energy because when we hear the word energy in English, we think like maybe warm, warm,
warm, warm, right?
Or, you know, electricity.
Electricity, you know, fossil fuels and policies regarding them in the government, right?
The Department of Energy.
like literally, you know.
And I think this kind of works, maybe not perfectly, but literally, you know, and he, uh, it means in working.
So it is true to say that what's a butterfly.
I know, I know it doesn't work with every single word.
But you know, God as he works in creation, as he acts sort of. Yeah, sort of. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Sorta.
So this is a category that we just we see to find the inner yeah, the Greek word.
that we see broken down.
like a lot of other categories in, for example, Aristotle.
Right. So Aristotle distinguishes between dynamis, right?
Which you may hear yelled in liturgy at a certain point.
Sometimes you'll hear it translated in English as with strength, which is weak
sauce. But I think we should just go straight, J.J. Walker, if you have to translate
it, have the priest yell, die to my.
But what's the deacon, you know, I know you don't have a deacon, but it's I don't have a deacon who gets to say that I am the deacon. Yeah.
I own the deacon.
I still can't do still.
I wear many hats.
Photos please picture didn't happen. Yeah, I can't find them. My head's too big.
So,
But what Denimese often gets translated in English as power or ability.
But it's not, for example, when Aristotle describes it, just an abstract ability or someone
being powerful or something, but it's directly related to the person who has that capability.
So examples, these are actually examples that Aristotle gives.
So you have a person that person has the ability to sleep.
Right.
They have the ability to go to sleep.
Even if they're not sleeping right now, right?
If they were not able to go to sleep, they would die.
Right.
So, if you have a living human there, they have the ability to go to sleep.
They have the ability to dance.
Right.
You can dance if you want to.
But, but,
that dynamism is not just the ability to dance.
It is the person with the ability to dance.
And then parallel to that,
and again, on the other side,
and again, is not sleeping or dancing.
It's not just the activity.
But, and again, is the person sleeping
or the person dancing.
It is the person in action, not just the act.
So when we talk about the divine energies, we talk about the energies of God.
What we're talking about is God Himself at work, God Himself acting in His creation.
This is why you will hear when Orthodox people talk about the essence, energy distinction.
He will say, we don't know God in His essence, but we do.
no God in his energies. That is real knowledge of God that comes from we encounter God in action.
Right in creation. Yeah. That's where we meet him. That's where we come to know him in person.
Right. Is in his working in creation. So do not let Plato brain mess this up for you.
right this is not
God is he quote unquote really is and then some kind of impression of God that we derive from things in creation.
Yeah, or like an emanation.
Right. That's not what this is.
Yeah.
Right. This is God as he is in himself.
God as he knows himself.
Right. Which we can't know.
Verses the God we encounter, the God we meet.
who is acting in the creation.
So energies are also God Himself.
And we have to say one more very important thing about God's activities,
his energies, these activities in which we encounter him.
That is that all of them are eternal.
All of them are eternal, meaning when we talk about God's activities, we talk about the
NRAA, we talk about the works of God, we're not talking about things that God does at an
individual time and an individual place.
We're not like last Tuesday at 10.05 a.m. local time.
healed this boy in Kenya. And then seven minutes later in Sri Lanka, he caused this girl to
repentance. And then, right, like, that's not what we're talking about. We're talking about
God's actions. God's actions are all continual and eternal. Because God is not within space and time.
Yeah, but we hum
humans, right? We humans have our human encounters with God within space and time, right?
So God is pouring out His love on creation. God is present, loving His whole creation
eternally. But I encounter Him there at certain points in my life, right? This is revealed
to me at certain points in my life.
And in certain ways, like it's not always the same.
Right.
Yeah.
These are beyond that.
So a good example of this in the Old Testament that we've talked about in the show before
is the name Yahweh.
Right.
The name Yahweh as we pointed out means he who causes to be.
And one of the phrases we see again and again in the Hebrew Bible is God saying when
then this happens.
then you will know that I am Yahweh.
This gets kind of hidden in the English
because then you will know I'm the Lord.
Well, that reads differently.
But what he's saying is then you will know I am the one
who causes things to be.
So we could say through Ezekiel to the exiles,
the judites and exiles.
When I have raised you up from your graves,
then you will know that I am Yahweh.
Right. He can say about both the Egyptians and the Israelites. When I have brought you out of Egypt with a mighty hand, then you will know that I am Yahweh.
Yeah. Right.
He's always Yahweh.
Right. He's always creative. He's always.
Yeah.
It's not that he's sometimes Yahweh. Right. He's always Yahweh.
But individual people and groups of people encounter him there.
then you will know.
It come to know him there. Yeah, right at a point in time from their perspective
right and I use that very deliberately because the Greek translation of Yahweh on
St. Gregory Paul Moss lists is one of the energies of God
Hmm
So he very much at least interpret it that way
Oh, wait, sorry, I just quoted a church father. I'll stop
Well, I'll have to do that on this show. What was I thinking?
So, in a sense, you can say, good it means, right, defining good in terms of God, right?
Good is what God does. If by that you understand that we're talking about the divine energies,
These eternal divine energies.
Right, the-
God who we encounter in action within the creation.
You can also say, sort of looking all at all of that collectively, right?
Because again, God isn't doing one thing at one time and another thing at another time,
right?
We can talk about there being these different, divine energies, these different activities
of God, but they're really all united.
one of the sort of classical examples of this, of how they're united.
is in your house you light a fireplace.
And the fire, that one fire, sitting there burning,
it lights the room and it heats the room.
Lighting the room and heating the room
are not the same thing.
You could distinguish those as two separate things.
But the fire isn't really alternating
back and forth between doing two different things.
And it's not really doing two things at once like multitasking.
Right. So this is the example that's given for how God, it's not like God is
well sometimes he's loving and sometimes he's creating and sometimes he's establishing justice and some right.
Yeah. And it's not that he's multitasking.
But these activities are united. Right. They're all
They're all part and parcel of each other. This is why you get like
these lists in St. Paul's epistle.
where he talks about how God is making us holy and making us just and glorifying us and
and and, right? Because these aren't like separate things, right? These are God's activity
to our life is doing all of these things, right? And so looking at it in that unified collective
way, you could say, good is the divine nature, because the divine nature is the sort of some
total of all of
the powers of God, which are always in action.
So if this is what we mean by good when we're talking about God,
is we're talking about, we're saying good is God's activity.
God is good is talking about the God who we encounter in that activity.
then what does it mean for humanity to be good?
For a human to be good.
Not just in counter distinction to evil, not just over against a human being evil.
We mentioned that last half.
Yeah, yeah.
And I think just to kind of underline that,
sometimes people have the sense that being good is just, I didn't do any bad things.
Right.
Just not.
And you know, yeah.
Like that's the kind of the
the parenting now be good. That's what we mean by that is don't do any bad things.
Yeah, keep it neutral. Yeah. Right. But so we we define what it means for a human to be evil, I think
because we've talked about it before. We didn't go into great depth. But we summarized it,
I think, well, the second half that a human being evil means you're under the control of sin,
you're enslaved to sin. Right. And that's that's bringing about destruction and decay for you and for
for the creation of a
around you. That's what it means for a human to be evil.
And we said, well, we give kind of a provisional definition of good over against that. But now,
now that we've come to hopefully a little better understanding of what it means for God to
be good, now we can come to a better understanding of what it means for a human to be good.
in some at least similar sense.
And this happens through a...
And this happens through the fact that our human nature, that we all share, the one human
nature that we all share with each other and with Christ, is the image of the divine nature.
Yeah.
Theomorphic.
That's what we are.
And you didn't know that was a spoiler, or what Father Andrew said it earlier.
That's true.
Yeah.
Sorry, everybody.
And we've talked about how our nature being in the
because nature itself is kind of a verbal category.
We've talked about how nature is sort of like the way body was used in the ancient world,
that it's this nexus of powers and potentialities.
That imaging God, being God's image, or bearing God's image,
is this verbal idea, it's about what we do.
Right. And we can see how the
human activity, because humans have an energy too, human nature has an energy too.
The human activity that is imaging God is good in multiple senses.
So when a human is imaging God, when a human is working to bring order and life to the
world. This
about human flourishing. So we can say that the human doing that is good in that sense, right,
in that he's flourishing as a human, right? We can talk about it in terms of, again,
throughout the word teleology, right? In terms of this person is becoming human, he's coming to
maturity. He's becoming what a human was created to be.
We can say that it's good because he is becoming like God who is good.
Because we establish that God is good and the God re-encounter in his activity is good,
when a human is participating in those activities, we can say that the human is good,
because it's the same activities.
And of course, the human is, definitionally here, when he's doing good,
is participating in.
God's energies and God's activities in the world.
Right?
And this is, we've talked about, but taking this down again.
God is at work as we said, eternally, loving His creation.
So when we love each other and we show love to another human being,
right?
And we truly are showing love, that's not our love, that's God's love.
Right.
God is loving that other person through us.
We are participating in what God is doing in the world.
And when God is healing, when God is establishing justice
and order, all the things that God does, we participate in them.
We don't just mimic.
It's not an external like mimicking.
Yeah.
Right.
But it is, it is, we are actively participating in what he is doing
such that he's doing it through us and in us.
Right, and that is transformative of us.
So then last kind of question within this context,
it comes up in this whole discussion of good and evil, of course, is,
do people have a free will?
What does it mean to have a free will?
Yeah, and most of the time when people think about free will,
what they think is,
I can choose to do good, I can choose to do evil.
and because I can choose between these things
Or I can choose to have chocolate I can choose to have vanilla because I can choose between these things
That means I have free will I am free. Whoo. Yeah. Yes
What if there's 31 flavors of ice cream is that too much
Yeah, I need 31 flavors
Right, but so we have to come to this question from a different perspective now, right?
Right.
All of those different views we talked about in the first half would come at this question
from different perspectives.
From Sam Harris saying, no, there is no free will.
To most natural law advocates saying, yes, there's a free will unless you're talking about
Calvin's view of natural law, which no, you don't have a free will.
But we have to approach it from everything we've been saying.
That's how we have to approach this question.
you
From what we've been saying, human nature has an energy.
So we as a human person, we have an activity.
We can act in the world.
We can act in the world in accordance with our nature.
But we've talked about that the question of sin and good.
Alright, is not a question of just choosing the
a rule or choosing to break a rule, making a good decision, making a bad decision.
Right.
So we've talked about what sin really is, is participating in sin, but participating in
sin as a particular character.
Remember sin is crouching at your door and wants to master you.
Sin enslaves you.
Fathers talk about the sinful passions because they're passions because they make you passive.
They act on you.
rather than you acting.
So the person who is sinning, the person who is living a life of sin is a person who is
entraped by sin and slaved by sin.
They are not free.
They may claim they're very free.
Because they may say, I'm free to indulge my desires.
I'm free to do that. I'm free to do that's not freedom though.
That's not freedom. That's what enslavement looks like.
It's enslavement to those desires.
But we've also said that doing good is not just like making good decisions,
or choosing to do the right thing.
Yeah. That we figured out through some philosophical calculus.
Make good choices. Yeah.
But that good is when we're participating in the divine energies,
when we're participating in God's activity.
the world. When we do that then we become free as God is free because we begin to flourish.
We come alive. And that is real freedom. Real freedom is freedom to flourish as what
you are as a human person.
If they do an ad-
to show this podcast for dogs, I'll have to change that. But, um,
see that, well, that's what I was not expecting for you. It's right.
There is television for dogs. I don't know if you know this.
I didn't know that.
It's mostly birds and squirrels and stuff. It's stuff that dogs find mesmerizing to look at.
But anyway,
I think we can start a division.
I can't deny division.
try to convert my heathen dogs.
Well, when you've converted your heathen dogs,
then they can come work for us.
OK.
Right.
So real freedom.
It's freedom to flourish as a human.
It's not just choosing one flavor of ice cream or the other.
What kind of breakfast cereal or the other?
It's not just choosing to do a thing.
Freedom is when...
when we are participating in God's activity as creation.
This is why I'm gonna refer to another church father.
St. Max's The Confessor talks about how in the age to come,
we will all be free because we won't be able to sin.
Right?
Let that sentence sink in.
Right.
Yeah.
Because we won't be able to sin,
we will finally all be free.
Go completely.
So, yeah, freedom to destroy yourself is not freedom.
Right? Self-destruction is not freedom.
Rebellion is not freedom.
This is the message you were supposed to get from Fight Club,
but didn't because you thought Tyler Dern was cool.
He's not cool.
Right? He needs to die for you to become a mature adult.
Right?
Self-deserved, it's not freedom.
Hey, man.
So for my fun of thoughts, I made reference earlier
to the, as you insist on saying it, D-D-K.
And I wanted to actually just quote the beginning of it
because I thought this is a good way to summarize
a lot of what we've been saying.
So it.
It's a short document, everybody, by the way.
You can read the whole thing on the internet.
There are multiple translations available.
It's called DID, A-C-H-E.
That's how it usually is in English translations.
And the beginning goes like this.
There are two ways, one of life and one of death,
but a great difference between the two ways.
The way of life, then, is this.
First.
You shall love God who made you,
second, love your neighbor as yourself,
and do not do to another what you would not want done to you.
And of these things the teaching is this,
bless those who curse you and pray for your enemies,
and fast for those who persecute you.
For what reward is there for loving those who love you,
do not the Gentiles do the same.
But love those who hate you,
and you shall not have an enemy.
And it goes on.
And it would be easy to read this document as a kind of list of things you're supposed
to do and things you're not supposed to do.
And honestly, if you read it that way and you do all the things it says to do and you
don't do the things it says not to do, you will be a saint.
No matter how you understand it, if you obey what's there, you will be a saint.
you do everything that it says in this document and abstain from what it says not to.
do. But sometimes it's easier to obey things if we understand them at a deeper level.
And I think it's notable that it starts out that way there's a way of life and a way
of death. And it says the way of life then is this. And notice that nothing is in the
part that I read that's not in the scriptures. In fact, most of this document you'll find
parallel passages in the scriptures.
If you know the gospel as well, you know that I just referenced them as I was reading the beginning of this this document
But notice this says first love God who made you second love your neighbor as yourself
Right, this is again straight out of scripture, but also it says again straight-up scripture bless those occurs you pray for your enemies fast for those who persecute you
What does all this come to?
It's really about...
doing the works of God, right? Does God not bless those who curse him? Does he not do good to his enemies? Does he not love them? He didn't not die for his enemies?
Right? Did he not undergo suffering for the sake of those who had turned their backs on him? Right?
Right? This is what God does. So when we do these things, it's not just like, okay, here's a list of stuff here.
you're supposed to do, it's doing the things that God does.
And this document describes this as the way of life.
Not the way of doing what's right.
It is that, but it is the way of life, meaning that you have life if you do these things.
You will find life in them.
It goes on to say, for instance, give to everyone who asks you, don't ask back.
These are words of Christ, really, right?
you
on and on and it's about love especially for those who are not loving you back and indeed sometimes
not just not loving you back but hurting you back hurting you back again these are the works of
God and um you know in daily life like right how does that work out well number one this is a very
practical document do what it says don't do the things this is not to do um
But also...
Also, like I'll give you an example from my life, right?
So I'm a parent.
I have four children.
My wife is a much better parent than I.
And together, we try to train our children
to behave in this way, to do these things, right?
And as we're trying to learn them ourselves,
what's the point of that?
It's so that...
We can live the commandments of God because as it says over and over and over and over and over again in the scriptures if you love God you will keep his commandments.
Christ himself said that it's in many places in the Bible.
You know, do a little word searching on Bible gateway or wherever you'll see love love God keep the commandments.
These things always go together.
When you do that, it leads to flourishing.
It's not just you have a very nice record, you know.
Look at all his achievements.
No, it's flourishing.
You are being what a human is meant to be.
Right?
And when you're training children,
or training anyone who's in your care,
or training yourself,
in many ways it is like keeping a garden.
Like you can't make the growth come,
but you can put all the conditions in place
for the growth to be possible.
It is God who gives the growth.
Right? We can water and, you know,
and all this kind of stuff, but it is God who gives the growth because, because.
What is the growth? It is to become like God. The reason that we follow the
commandments is not so that we will be known as good people. The reason that we
follow the commandments is not so that we have some spotless record. The reason
that we follow the commandments is because it makes us like God.
This is the path of theosis.
This is the path of being divinized or deified,
of becoming as Christ says, equal to the angels.
That's what this is because this is what the angels do.
This is how the saints live.
So if we want to be like them, then this is what we do.
And there's an actual purpose to following the commandments.
And so we say that God is good.
and by that we mean this is what God is doing in the world, this is who God is, this is how he acts.
Right? Then for us to join ourselves to that, to do those same things, to have him acting through us,
is then to become like God. And as Father said, not just in an imitative way, not just emulating him,
But in a participatory way, God is working through us and that trans...
forms us to be elevated, to become what humans were destined to be when we were created.
Sons of God equal to the angels co-raining with Christ forever and ever.
That's why all this matters. Father.
So to bring up
Aristotle again, this is my want.
Aristotle understood that there's this direct connection between ethics and politics.
And so his somewhat problematic ethics was coordinate with a very problematic politics, from, not
not just our modern perspective, but from any Christian perspective.
And this is sort of true across the board, right?
This is true across the board in the sense that at whatever level of community we're talking
about, right, whether we're talking about a local community, a neighborhood, a workplace,
a city state government right of any size a national government.
The leadership is whether they like it or not, they're going to be structuring things
in a way that is coordinate with and ultimately promoting and inculcating a certain view of
What a human person is of what human nature is and of what a good person and a bad person.
person is. That's good of very all over the place. So North Korea, you know, a good
person is a good citizen who loves dear leader. And a bad person is one who does not.
A good person in another society might be the one who works hard or the one who
accumulates well.
or the one who has power or the one who
founds charities or the one right.
But this will all be coordinated with some kind of ethical view.
I think I can safely say that none of the folks
who are going to listen to this are in a country
where their civil government really has struck
the society in a way to promote the flourishing of every human person. As that
flourishing is understood within Christianity, right? They may pay lip service
to that idea, right? Lots of governments have paid lip service to that idea,
like a lot of free market American folks in the 1950s would say that, so at a
A lot of people in the 1950s install its Russia say that.
But what flourishing means is not really subjective in the sense that it's not really negotiable
because humans actually do have a nature and we all share the same one.
And so it's no more subjective when we talk about human flourishing than it is when we talk about like an oak tree flourishing.
Right.
No one would look at an oak tree that's full of rot,
or that's run up against the foundation of a house,
or that's pulling up out of the ground
and about to tip over and say,
no, no, by my definition, this tree is flourishing.
Human flourishing is not any more subjective.
It is a real thing.
There have been movements,
social
throughout modern history, throughout the period of time when such social movements were possible and became a thing.
To try to topple governments or reform governments in such a way that at least the people who sometimes a series of waves of people who take power through violence,
each tries to restructure the society in a way
that will promote their definition of human flourishing.
Or something else. Sometimes they don't even paint lip servers to that, but to promote something.
It's pretty clear that that's not a way forward.
That that's ultimately utopian.
That's we can through our human efforts and human reasoning,
structure utopia, the good place, right?
The perfect place, the perfect order in which everyone flourishes and everyone has everything they want.
And there's no strife and no trouble and everything will be perfect if we can just do this.
And the road toward that is just littered with dead bodies.
It's covered in massacres and atrocities, all of which are justified by the goal.
And I'm saying this because I want to make very clear
when we're talking about human flourishing of this kind of thing in this episode
that that's not where we're going.
But if humans are going to flourish, they do need to be in communities
that are structured around human flourishing, actual human flourishing.
And there's only one place this can start.
That's church communities.
That's where it started.
in the Roman Empire. That's where it started in the Persian Empire. That's where it started
everywhere in the world. The Christian community can be and has to be if it's really going
to be a Christian community. Structured in such a way. Led in such a way. Participated
in such a way that the humans would become a part of it begin to flourish.
come alive. We've said how that happens. It's through encountering God in his work in the world.
Not just encountering God in liturgy, encountering God in the sacraments. That's included, right?
Not just that, but it is actions in the world within the community, his actions and the
activities in the world outside the community.
where we encounter him. And this is done in very concrete ways, very concrete ways.
Humans need certain things in order to flourish. They need certain support. They need certain
material things, just to survive, let alone flourish. Our church communities are capable.
They are capable everyone.
of them is capable of meeting those needs for all the people in it. They are. If you look at me
and say, well, our church is too small or whatever, bowl, bowl. You just have a bunch of people who
aren't committed to it. You have a bunch of people who aren't committed to it who don't really
want to do that. Who have some other agenda? And that church community needs...
to be transformed.
It needs to repent, frankly.
Let's just use that word for it.
And transform and restructure itself.
Leadership needs to lead in a different direction,
until it becomes that kind of place.
And see, when it becomes that kind of place where the people
who come in are having all of those needs met and are able
to flourish and are able to truly live and truly be free,
a bunch of things are going to happen.
Let's get to start a tr-
a bunch of other people. It's going to start attracting a bunch of other people out in the world who are desperate for that, and there's no other place they can find it.
And they're going to start coming, and the community is going to grow.
However, this is the path that the church took over against the Roman Empire.
If you want the country you live in, to be a country.
They promote human flourishing. You don't stage a revolution. You don't start shooting at people. You don't storm the capital. You don't do any of those things.
You work in your church. You build that community. You meet the needs of the other people there.
You love them. You show compassion for them. You listen to them.
You be with them. You give them all the things that you do for us. You experience this flourishing yourself. You begin to
truly live and truly be free.
And then you remember that it's a long game.
Took 300 years for the Roman Empire.
You probably won't be alive to see it happen.
And that's okay.
That's okay.
People used to start building cathedrals
that their great, great grandchildren would get to worship in.
really used to do that. We can do that too. But it starts with us. It starts with you,
it starts with the other people, your parish and your church community, deciding that this
is what you want that place to be. And then making it happen. So those are my thoughts.
Amen. Well, that's the podcast.
for tonight. Thank you very much for listening everyone. If you were not able to get through to us
live or didn't leave a comment in our streams, we'd still like to hear from you. You can email us
at Lord of Spheres and Ancient Faith.com. You can send us some message at our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spheres. And if you have basic
questions, introductory questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help in finding a parish,
head on over to ortheroxintro.org.
Join us for a live broadcast on the second and fourth
Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific for another turning point for
Stuck in the Road. Time grabs you by the wrist and directs you where to go.
If you're on Facebook you can follow our page join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings everywhere, don't listen to Green Day, but most importantly share this show
with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally be sure to go to extrabake.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air. So make the best of this test and don't ask
Why it's not a question.
lesson learned in time.
Thank you, good night, and God bless you.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient
Faith Radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10-
thousand and thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and
riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.